Marian Storm papers SSC.MS.00156
Sophia Smith Collection
Marian Storm papers
1857-1972
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00156
18 boxes, 1 volume, oversize materials (9 linear feet)
Journalist, Author, Poet, Animal rights advocate, Conservationist. Papers include biographical materials; correspondence; drafts and research notes; photographs; memorabilia; artwork; journals; scrapbooks; and published and unpublished writings on Mexican society, culture, history, and natural history; animal welfare; nature and plant conservation; and travels in Central and South America, the Caribbean, and Europe.
Biographical / Historical
Marian Isabel Storm was born in Stormville, New York on January 30, 1892. She graduated from Smith College in 1913 and attended the Miller Business School for one year. She spent several years working in secretarial positions, including secretary to the Argentine Ambassador in Washington, D.C. from 1917 to 1918. She was also assistant editor for The Countryside Magazine from 1915 to 1917 and worked as a reporter and freelance writer for the New York Evening Post, 1918 to 1924, and later for the New York Tribune.
In the mid 1930s, she moved to Mexico where she spent the rest of her life, writing about Mexican plant life, animal life, and the human poverty she saw around her. She was the author of several books and articles, both fiction and non-fiction including Prologue to Mexico, The Life of Saint Rose, Hoofways into Hot Country, True Stories from Tarascan (1941), and Rights of Animals (1951). A conservationist, she single-handedly saved a Mexican flowering shrub, the Ayuque, from extinction and was made an honorary member of the Sociedad de Mexico in recognition of her efforts. She died in Guadalajara, Mexico on August 20, 1975.
Scope and Contents
The Marian Storm Papers include biographical information, correspondence, writings (in English and Spanish), drafts and research notes; photographs; memorabilia; correspondence and journals about her writings; and fifteen scrapbooks of clippings, essays and other writings. Storm's published and unpublished works include magazine and newspaper articles, poems, songs, short stories and a novel. Her prolific writings (in English and Spanish) cover such topics as Mexican society, culture, history, and natural history; animal welfare; nature and plant conservation; and travels in Central and South America, the Caribbean, and Europe. The collection includes original artwork by Mexican artist Silviano Rodriguez and a small amount of writings and correspondence of archeologist and historian of Ancient Mexico, Zelia Nuttall. Other correspondents include Lazaro Cardenas, former Mexican president.
Arrangement
This collection is organized as follows:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
SERIES III. WRITINGS
SERIES IV. MEXICO
SERIES V. TRAVEL
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
BOOKS ON SHELF
Conditions Governing Access
Due to their fragility, some materials may not be photocopied.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Marian Storm donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection between 1964 and 1976.
Animal welfare--Mexico--History--Sources; Humane education-Mexico--History--Sources; Mexico--Description and travel--Sources; Nature conservation--Mexico--History--Sources; Women artists--Biography--Sources; South America--Description and travel--Sources; Spain--Description and travel--Sources; Nuttall, Zelia, 1858-1933--Biography--Sources; Rodriguez, Silviano, 1892-1975; Storm family; correspondence; Writings; Research; clippings; scrapbooks; Works of art; photographs; memorabilia; Books; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Storm, Marian, 1892-1975; Rodriguez, Silviano; Storm, Marian; Kuster, Ellen
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Marian Storm (Box 1)
    - Passport, clippings, correspondence, and death report, 1940-75 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Photographs and negatives, 1897-1966; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Diary excerpts, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Smith College (Box 1)
      - Verse, 1910-11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Papers, 1910-13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Zelia Nuttall (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1923-29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Cult of the Sun": clippings, 1930-33 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, notes, and articles, 1922-33 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Publication list and pamphlets, 1894-1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  General
  [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS--Scrapbooks]
  - Family (includes clippings and pamphlet), 1903; 1955-69 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1934-69; undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personal (Box 1)
    - J. Raymond Bresson, Robert C. Thomas, and Delfina Ayala, 1935-72 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Odell D. Tompkins and Lazaro Cardenas, 1939-42 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Marion Halsey (Smith class of 1913), 1937-73 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Marcia Williams Bradley, 1966-68 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Re: Humane Treatment of Animals, 1944-71 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Re: "Tony" Trott, 1961-63 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Re: Marian Storm's poetry, 1959-61 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Addresses, undated (Box 1)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - Pamphlets and notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Short stories (unpublished), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typed articles and clippings, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bibliographies, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Editorials on plants and animals, 1933-41 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Foods: clippings and pamphlets, 1923-33 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Poems: clippings, pamphlets, and correspondence, 1923-34 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Humane Treatment of Animals,", undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Poems (by others) and book, 1920s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous writings and sheet music, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings and notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Unused chapter in Prologue to Mexico by Marian Storm, and correspondence, 1931-69 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Poems, 1922-23 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Prologue to Mexico, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stories from magazines (published), 1925-28 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes for unfinished novel, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Devil's Advocate: manuscript, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - St. Rose of Lima: notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Lady of the House books 1 and 2, undated (Box 4)
  - Publications (Box 4)
    - "Ayuque Flowers: Michoacan,", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Ditty for a Rebel": sheet music, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "For the Animals of Mexico,", 1913-1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "The Gallant Come Late,", 1928 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Hoofways into Hot Country, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Hymn for the Winter Solstice": sheet music, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Invitation": sheet music, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Life of St. Rose, 1937-55 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Minstrel Weather, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - "A Spray of Eglantine": sheet music and correspondence, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Rights of Animals: clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, flyers, and books, 1951-68 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
    - "Sun and Snow": correspondence, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - "The Tranquilizing Influence of Other Whales,", 1957 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Enjoying Uruapan: correspondence, clippings, cover painting, and copy of book, 1945-55 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Caminois de Herradura a Tierra Caliente [Hoofways Into Hot Country] (translated by Carlos Garcia Trejo), 2010 and DVD of receiption and introduction, 1945-55 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Typescripts (Box 5)
    - "Almost Persuaded,", undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - "The Ambassador's Apparel,", undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - "Company on Laurel,", undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - "Discovery,", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "Dismissal,", undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - "Don Genovevo's Dogs,", undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - "Eden,", undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - "The Extravagant Murder,", undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - "The Fantasie,", undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - "Father Putters Around,", undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "The Fixed Light,", undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "From the Mother of the Groom,", undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "Fruit,", undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - "The Gifted Henry Quakenbush,", undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - "Hosea and Jose,", undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "I Lived in Bronx Park,", undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - "The Learned Man of Lorja,", undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - "Mrs. Macklin's Charlie,", undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - "A Master of the Guild,", undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - "A Mountain Voice,", undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Mute Fate,', undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - "No Visitor in Twelve Years,", undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "The Old Place,", undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "Pastoral Call,", undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "The Patient Clock,", undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "A Question of Discipline,", undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "Tonight God Dies,", undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - "Rose Calverly,", undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - "The Second Flood,", undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - "Seek No Further,", undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "The Token,", undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "The Trout in the Wall,", undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "The Unexpected,", undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - "When Cactus Meets Pedestrian,", undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - "Why Santa and the Cid Made Good,", undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Writings by C. Goring and Jerry Bogardus, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
- SERIES IV. MEXICO
  - Edited editorials, 1939-41 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photographs and pamphlets, 1939-61 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Watering trough at Mazatlan: photographs and correspondence, 1945-47 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1923-32 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Tlahuicole (film in days of Montezuma): photographs, pamphlets, correspondence, and reports, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Herbs and medicinal plants: photographs, pamphlets, notes, and correspondence, 1911-40 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Laquers, notes, articles, and correspondence, 1934-36 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Songs, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Musical instruments (Chrimias-shawn): notes, correspondence, pamphlets, and photographs, 1934-38 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Natural history: photographs, pamphlets, correspondence, paintings, and notes, 1935-43 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Ayugue (Balmea Stormae): pamphlets, articles, correspondence, and certificate, 1941-72 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Wild dahlias: photographs, notes, correspondence (with Marshall A. Howe), and pamphlet, 1932-36 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Natural history, euphorbia: notes, correspondence, and pamphlet, 1937-38 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Orchids: photos, notes, and correspondence, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Pottery: notes, correspondence, and certificate of receipt, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Religion (churches): notes, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Fiestas and Saints day: photographs and notes, 1934-36 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "El Rollo": photographs, notes, and paintings, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Uruapan: photographs, notes, prints, bank book, and clippings, 1933-37 (Box 9, Folder 9-11)
  - Miscellaneous: correspondence and notes, 1936-38 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Volcanic eruption and ruins: photographs and notes, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Writings by Marshall H. Saville: pamphlets, 1899-1909 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- SERIES V. TRAVEL
  - Protection of animals: clippings, 1955-68 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Maps: clippings, pamphlets, and maps, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous: notes, clippings, and pamphlets, 1924-34 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Art: postcards, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Protection of animals: pamphlets and flyers, 1947-72 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    [see also box 11]
  - Silviano Rodriguez: biographical information, pamphlet, correspondence, and paintings, 1913-43 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
  - Storm King Mountain: clippings, correspondence, and pamphlets, 1966-67 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Articles (Box 10)
    - Bolivia: clippings and pamphlet, 1932 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Caribbean Islands and Mexico, 1927 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Peru: clippings and photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Spain: pamphlets, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Virgin Islands: photographs, clippings, and pamphlets, 1918-29 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Campana Nacional Protection de Animales: photo-engraved relief blocks for printing (Box 11)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Scrapbooks (15): writings, correspondence, memorabilia, and clippings, 1916-60 (Box 12-17)
  - Watercolors of Mexico by Silviano Rodriguez, 1934-1943; undated (Box 18)
    List with titles in box 10, folder 6.
  - Colored pencil sketch by Lillian R. Field, undated (Box 18)
  - Posters and printed material regarding the humane treatment of animals, undated (Box 18)
  - Watercolors of Mexico by Silviano Rodriguez, 1934-1943; undated (Map-case Flat File)
  - Watercolor painting by Mina Winelow, undated (Map-case Flat File)
    Missing as of January 2016.
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Old Dirk's Book, by Raymond Storm, 1949